provenexpert.com 2019-09-09

# Privacy Policy

Thank you for your interest in our company. The protection of your data is important to us, so we have made it our mission to safeguard and protect your data and your rights in relation to data.

Table Of Contents

  * 1\. What personal data do we collect?
  * 2\. From whom is personal data collected?
  * 3\. Why we collect personal data and what we use it for
  * 4\. Disclosure of personal data
  * 5\. Duration for which we store personal data
  * 6\. Rights of the person affected – which rights do you have in relation to your personal data stored by us?
  * 7\. Use of cookies

Part 3: Our Privacy Policy in detail  
A. Detailed information about the processing of user and customer data

  * 1\. What personal data do we collect?
  * 2\. From whom is personal data collected?
  * 3\. Why we collect personal data and what we use it for
  * 4\. Disclosure of personal data
  * 5\. Duration for which we store personal data
  * 6\. How we protect your personal data

B. Detailed information about the use of our website

  * 1\. General data and information collection
  * 2\. Registration on our website
  * 3\. Subscription to our newsletter
  * 4\. Newsletter tracking
  * 5\. Blog comment feature
  * 6\. Contact options via the websites
  * 7\. Use and application of third party tools and services on our websites
  * 8\. Privacy policy for the payment methods offered

C. Your rights regarding the processing of personal data in detail

  * 1\. Right to access information
  * 2\. Right to correction
  * 3\. Right to deletion (Right to be forgotten)
  * 4\. Right to restrict processing
  * 5\. Right to data portability
  * 6\. Right to objection
  * 7\. Right to revoke data protection consent
  * 8\. Right of appeal to a regulatory body

D. Our legal basis for the processing of your data

  * 1\. Legitimate interest
  * 2\. Agreement
  * 3\. Assertion, exercise or defence of legal rights

Part 4 - Definitions

Part 1 - Introduction

Personal data such as names, addresses, email addresses and telephone numbers are always processed in accordance with the General Data Protection Regulation, as well as with the country-specific data protection regulations relevant to us. This Privacy Policy contains information about the type of data that we collect, the extent to which we collect data and its purpose, and also about the rights that you have, provided that personal data has been collected or processed.

In the context of our data protection declaration we use various legal and technical terms. Explanations can be found here.

As the persons responsible for data processing, we have implemented numerous technical and organizational measures to ensure that the personal data processed by us is protected as completely as possible. Internet-based data transfer can however create security gaps, which means that absolute protection cannot be guaranteed. For this reason, you also have the option to communicate personal data to us through alternative methods, i.e. by telephone.

This data protection declaration applies to the personal data of our customers and suppliers as well as visitors to our websites. 

The company ("Expert Systems AG" or "we") responsible for data processing within the meaning of the applicable data protection laws (including, among others, the Basic Data Protection Regulation (Regulation (EU) 2016/679) (the "DSG-VO") is the:

 **Expert Systems AG**  
Quedlinburger Str. 1  
10589 Berlin  
Germany

E-Mail: [privacy@provenexpert.com](mailto:privacy@provenexpert.com)  
Websites: all websites and services of Expert Systems AG

We have designated a central contact person for all data protection-related questions to safeguard the interests of all those affected by data processing. You can contact us at:

 **Expert Systems AG**  
Jan Reimann  
Quedlinburger Str. 1  
10589 Berlin  
Germany

E-Mail: [privacy@provenexpert.com](mailto:privacy@provenexpert.com)  
Websites: All Expert Systems AG websites and services

You can contact our contact person directly at any time with any questions and suggestions regarding data protection.

Important: Please note that this privacy policy may change from time to time. Please use this page to inform yourself, as we will post any changes here.  
If you do not agree with a certain aspect of our Privacy Policy, you are entitled to certain legal rights, where applicable. These are described in the respective section below.

Part 2 - Summary: Our Privacy Policy at a glance

**1\. What personal data do we collect?**

**General personal data of our users:**  
If you are a user of our product provenexpert.com, we must collect and use certain personal data in order to provide services for you, such as: (1) providing a profile, and (2) information and offers that may be useful to you.

A more detailed description of the personal data we collect in this way can be found here.

 **Customer data:**  
Should you choose to use services of ours which require payment, we will additionally collect and store your account and/or credit card information. These will then be requested separately as part of the activation of your desired service package.

A detailed description of which personal data we collect in this way can be found in the section entitled "Our Privacy Policy in detail" here.

 **General personal data of our users and customers:**  
When you create reviews, we generally store only your email address and the associated log file as inventory data (see a. above). You have the option to volunteer other information, such as your name or company name, which we will also store.

A more detailed description of the personal data we collect in this way can be found here.

 **Visitors to our websites:**  
We collect a limited amount of data from visitors to the website. This is to facilitate navigation on our websites and to better manage the services that we offer to you. The data we collect in this way comprises information about how you use our website and how often you access it.

For more information about what information we collect about you when you visit our websites can be found here.

**2\. From whom is personal data collected?**

**General personal data of our users:**  
We generally only collect your personal data directly from you.

Exception:  
If you are a member of an association or other organization with which we have a framework agreement, we may collect your data related to that organisation.

**Customer data:**  
We generally only collect your personal data directly from you.

Exception:  
If you are a member of an association or other organization with which we have a framework agreement, we may collect your data related to that organisation.

We generally only collect your account information and/or credit card details directly from you.

**General personal data of evaluators of our users and customers:**  
We only collect your personal data directly from you.

**Visitors to our websites:**  
When you visit the website, we automatically collect data using cookies in accordance with the cookie settings in your browser. More information about cookies, such as how we use them and which options are available to you can be found in in the section entitled "Our Privacy Policy in detail" here. We also collect information from you when you contact us through the websites, for example when you enter information on a contact form, chat, or comment on a post on our blog.

Generally, we may collect certain data automatically as soon as you access our website or read or click on an email from us. For more information on this topic can be found here.

**3\. Why we collect personal data and what we use it for**

**General personal data of our users & Customer data**  
We collect and use information about our customers (i.e. users) primarily to make sure that the contractual agreement between you and MAGIX is properly implemented in order to ensure a smooth business relationship. For example, we need personal data to process orders and to provide the services you have ordered (service packages). A user account, which stores personal data, is required to use our products.  
We also partly require personal data from you in order to provide you with our services (such as customer support) in the best possible way.

More information about how we use your personal data can be found here.

**General personal data of the evaluators of our users and customers**  
When you submit a review, we collect your personal data to prevent misuse (e.g. through multiple reviews).

**Visitors to our websites:**  
We use your data to to facilitate navigation on our website, for example to display offers and/or information, which we think will be of interest to you.

More information about cookies, such as how we use them and which options are available to you can be found in in the section entitled "Our Privacy Policy in detail" here.

**4\. Disclosure of personal data**

**General personal data of our users & Customer data**  
We pass on your data for the following purposes: (1) Primarily to ensure that you can use our product (e.g. transfer to Telekom as hosting service provider), (2) to payment service providers such as PayPal. 

An overview of the categories of recipient to whom your personal data can be given can be disclosed in the section entitled "Our Privacy Policy in detail" here.

**General personal data of the evaluators of our users and customers**  
We pass on your data exclusively for the purpose of enabling you to submit a rating (transfer to Telekom as a hosting service provider).

**Visitors to our websites:**  
Unless you specify otherwise, we can give your information to web analytics service providers, affiliate networks, marketing automation platforms and social media services, in order to ensure that you only receive appropriately targeted advertisements.

In general, we reserve the right to also transmit your data to other countries outside of the EU or EEA. In this case, we will however ensure a minimum level of data protection corresponding to the GDPR level of protection, through the appropriate arrangements.

**5\. Duration for which we store personal data**

The criteria for the duration of storage for personal data is the respective legal retention period, after which the data will be deleted. In addition to this, we save the respective data only provided that they are still necessary for the fulfillment of a contract.

More information about our basic procedures relating to storage of personal data can be found in the section entitled "Our Privacy Policy in detail" here.

**6\. Rights of the person affected – which rights do you have in relation to your personal data stored by us?**

Even if we already hold your personal data, you are entitled to various rights with regard to this information. If you would like to talk to us regarding this, please do not hesitate to contact us. We will make every effort to take care of your query as soon as possible and every case will be treated in accordance with applicable legal regulations. Please note that we may record our communication in order to better solve the issues raised by you.

Insofar as we save your personal data, certain legal rights apply (the "rights of the person affected"), which we will outline here. More information about individual rights can be found here.

  * **Right to access information**  
At any time, you have the right to request us to confirm which information we have saved about you, and to request that this information be changed, updated, or deleted. We can then comply with your request. We also have the following options:
    * We may ask you to confirm your identity, or request further information, and
    * provided that this is permitted by law, we can decline your request. In this case, we will explain the reasons for doing so.
  * **Right to objection:**  
If we use your data because we believe this is in our legitimate interests and you do not agree, you have the right to object. We will respond to your request within 30 days. In certain cases, we are entitled to extend this period. We will usually only disagree in very narrowly defined circumstances.
  * **Right to revoke consent:**  
If we have obtained your consent to process your personal data for specific activities (for example, in order to send you advertisements), you can revoke this consent at any time.
  * **Right to correction**  
You have the right to request that the personal data concerning you be immediately corrected or amended.
  * **Right to deletion**  
In certain situations (for example, if we have unlawfully processed your data) you have the right to request us to delete your personal data. We will reply to your request within 30 days (in certain cases, we may however have the right to extend this period) and we will only disagree in very specific, narrowly defined circumstances – for example, if the data is absolutely necessary in order to continue to provide our services to you or to ensure the protection of our intellectual property. If we agree to your request, we will delete your data, but we will generally assume that you wish your name to be included in the list of persons that do not want to be contacted. In this way, we minimize the chance that you will be contacted in the future should your data be collected separately under other circumstances. If you do not wish this, please let us know.
  * **Right to restrict processing**  
Instead of requesting deletion, you can also request from us that the processing of your data be restricted or blocked. We will also reply to this request within 30 days, except if we still need the data, for example in order to continue to provide our services to you or to ensure the protection of our intellectual property.
  * **Right to data portability**  
Should you wish, you have the right to transfer your data from us to another person responsible. We will support you by transferring your data directly for you or by providing you with a copy in a standard machine-readable format.
  * **Rights relating to automated decisions (profiling)**  
Under certain circumstances, you have the right not to be subject to a decision that has been based exclusively on automated processing and that will have legal effect against you. However, under certain circumstances we may have a legitimate interest in such automated decision-making.
  * **Right of appeal to a regulatory body**  
You also have the right to lodge a complaint with a local regulatory body. Details on this topic can be found here.

**7\. Use of cookies**

Our websites/web services use "cookies". Cookies are small text files that are saved on the hard drive of your PC (client) for a defined period.

Most cookies we use are deleted at the end of the browsing session (known as session cookies).  
Other cookies stay on your computer and allow us to recognize your computer on your next visit ( (permanent or persistent cookies).  
Cookies usually contain a "cookie ID". This is a pseudonymized date in the form of a unique cookie identification.  
It consists of a series of characters that can be used to associate websites and the servers with a specific Internet browser (client) in which the cookie is saved.

Cookies are generally distinguished into first and third party cookies.

First party cookies will only be assigned by the website that you are currently on (for example, the website under the domain provenexpert.com).  
Expert Systems AG uses first party cookies for essential website functions, like for storing website settings, restoring sessions and for securing your session data.

Within this process, access only occurs in impersonalized form and exclusively when you visit our website. Other websites cannot access this information.  
To ensure the data security of our visitors, it is necessary to allow first party cookies in order to use provenexpert.com .

Third party cookies are set by a third party provider that has been authorized by Expert Systems AG, i.e. not by the actual website that you are currently viewing.

By using these cookies, we can adjust our offers to best meet customer preferences and can make browsing our site as convenient as possible for you (advertising, conversion tracking and personalization).

In addition, we use third party providers in order to collect online statistics (analytics) as a basis for measuring the success of our advertising offers and subsequently improving them.  
Even when cookies from third party providers are used, data is only accessed in an anonymized form.

An overview of third parties on our websites can be found here in the section entitled "Use and application of third party tools and services on our websites".

All essential services from our website/web services essentially work without the use of third party cookies.

You may prevent the installation of cookies anytime by selecting the option "Do not accept cookies" in your browser. In addition, you can at any time delete cookies via your Internet browser or another software program. This can be done with any standard Internet browser.

Part 3: Our Privacy Policy in detail

A. Detailed information about the processing of user and customer data

**1\. What personal data do we collect?**

**General personal data of our users & Customer data:**  
We collect some data about our customers and users that we require to deliver our products and implement contracts and for license management. We therefore require your name, your email address and country of residence in order to create a user account, which is then used to order service packages. The same information is collected when you register for our newsletter. We may also require further information from you (e.g. address, telephone number or date of birth) to order of services. You may also provide us with further data - this is optional. The specific data collected depends on the form or input mask used, or as requested by our support staff over the phone.

If for any reason we require additional personal data from you, we will let you know.

We analyze the use of our products with Google Analytics. Here, specific computer data (including your computer's hardware key, processor name etc.) is used to create a pseudonymized profile, which collects usage data in order to improve our products. For more information on this topic can be found here.

**General personal data of evaluators of our users and customers:**  
When you create reviews, we generally store only your email address and the associated log file as inventory data.  
You also have the option to enter your first and last name, which we will also save.  
**Visitors to our websites:**  
When normal Internet users visit our website, we save data to what are known as log files. Log files consist of the IP address assigned by the Internet service provider to the computer making the request for that session, as well as the name and version of the Internet browser being used to visit the website.

We also use our own session cookies when you visit our website. The information we obtain from these include the type and version of your Internet browser, the website from which you came to our website, which pages you visited on our website, as well as the date and duration of your visit.

**2\. From whom is personal data collected?**

We generally only collect your personal data directly from you.

Exception:  
If you are a member of an association or other organization with which we have a framework agreement, we may collect your data related to that organisation.

**3\. Why we collect personal data and what we use it for**

User data:  
In general, we use information about our users or customers in the following ways:

**a) Advertising measures**  
We may send you information at regular intervals that we believe to be of interest to you, and also inform you of certain discounts and special offers to which you are entitled as a result of your business relationship with us. 

We require your consent for some aspects of these activities that are not covered by our legitimate interests (in particular for data collection using cookies and direct marketing to you through our digital channels). According to the circumstance, we will ask for your explicit consent via "opt-in" or silent consent via "soft opt-in" (see below).

Consent via "Soft opt-in" is a specific form of consent that applies if you have had business dealings with us before (e.g. you have ordered a product from us or registered a domain with us) and we may advertise other products or services within this context. For consent via "soft opt-in", we will consider your consent as provided, as long as you do not withdraw it.

You can revoke your consent at any time. For more information on this topic can be found here.

Our advertising as a whole is based on entities that we consider to be especially helpful to our customers and users. However, we are aware that we do not always do things the right way for everybody. We may use your data to display you advertisements and other Expert Systems AG content on other websites, e.g. Facebook. If you do not wish your data to be used in this way, please change the cookie settings in your browser, as described above. Even if you deactivate advertisement cookies, it's possible that you may continue to receive Expert Systems AG advertisements. If this happens, it is because the advertisement is targeted towards an anonymous target group and not towards you specifically.

**b) Functionality of our products and protection of our intellectual property rights**  
We are dependent on protecting our intellectual property rights, not least for the purposes of being able to offer you our products and services at their usual standard of quality and at attractive prices.  
In order to enable you to use our products, a user account is necessary, where certain data must be obligatorily saved (name, email address and country).

**c) Assertion, exercise or defence of legal claims**  
In unusual cases, we may also use your personal data in order to assert, exercise or defend legal rights.

We may use your personal data for these purposes if it corresponds with our legitimate interests. For more information on this topic and what that means can be found here.

**4\. Disclosure of personal data**

We may share your personal data with the following categories of people in a variety of ways and for a variety of purposes, as appropriate and in accordance with local laws and regulations:

  * All company groups
  * Tax authorities, audit authorities or other authorities, if we in good faith believe that we are required by law or other regulation to disclose such information (for example, because of a request from a tax authority or in connection with an anticipated legal dispute)
  * External service providers that provide services in our name (including external email providers, auditors and accountants, technical support)
  * Providers of external IT services and storage providers, if a corresponding arrangement (or similar assurance) exists
  * Marketing technology platforms and suppliers

If in future we merge with or are acquired by another company (or should meaningful discussion about such a possibility take place), we may disclose your personal data to the (future) new company owners.

In general, we reserve the right to also transmit your data to other countries outside of the EU or EEA. In this case, we will however ensure a minimum level of data protection corresponding to the GDPR level of protection, through the appropriate arrangements.

**5\. Duration for which we store personal data**

We process and save personal data solely for the duration necessary for achieving the purpose for which the data was stored, or as stipulated in laws and requirements set by the European directive and regulation provider or another legislator to which we are subject.

If the storage purpose ceases to apply or if a storage period prescribed by European directive and regulation provider or another competent legislator expires, the personal data will be blocked or deleted routinely and in accordance with the statutory provisions.

**6\. How we protect your personal data**

We will adopt all reasonable and appropriate measures to protect the personal information we have stored from misuse, loss or unauthorized access. To this end, we have taken a range of technical and organizational measures. This includes measures to deal with any suspected breaches of data.

If you believe that your personal data has been misused or has been lost or has been accessed without authority, please inform us immediately. Our contact details can be found in Part 1 of this Privacy Policy.

B. Detailed information about the use of our website

As mentioned above, we collect a limited amount of data from visitors to our websites in order to facilitate navigation of our websites and to better manage the services that we offer to you. You can use our websites without having to provide any personal data. In certain cases (e.g. Store orders, product activation etc.), processing of personal data may be required.

**1\. General data and information collection**

Our websites collect a variety of general data and information each time one of their pages is loaded. This general data and information is saved to our server log files. Data that may be collected includes (1) browser types used and their versions, (2) operating system used by the accessing system, (3) the website from which an accessing system reaches our websites (what is known as a "referrer"), (4) subpages on our websites that are accessed by an accessing system, (5) date and time of visit to websites, (6) an Internet Protocol Address (IP address) and (7) any other similar data and information, that could serve as hazard prevention in the event of an attack on our information technological systems.

No conclusions are drawn about the person concerned during the use of this general data and information. This information is required in order to (1) correctly transmit the content of our website, (2) optimize content of and advertising for our website, (3) guarantee the permanent functional operability of our information technology systems and technology for our website, and (4) in the event of a cyber attack, provide law enforcers with necessary information for prosecution. This anonymously collected data and information is therefore evaluated by Expert Systems AG statistically and also with the aim of increasing data protection and data security in our company ultimately to ensure an optimum level of protection for the personal data processed by us. Anonymous server log file data are stored separately from all personal data provided by a person concerned.

**2\. Registration on our website**

You can register your personal data on several of our websites, for instance by signing up to our newsletter or setting up a user account (e.g. by activating an Expert Systems AG product). The specific personal data you submit to Expert Systems AG is dependent on the type of input mask used for registration. The personal data submitted by the person concerned will be collected and stored for the sole purpose of internal use and purposes by Expert Systems AG. We may arrange for disclosure to one or more contract processors, for example a telecommunications provider, who also uses the personal data exclusively for an internal use that is attributable to us.

When registering on an Expert Systems AG website, the IP address provided by your Internet service provider (ISP), date and time of registration will also be stored. This data is stored against the background that the misuse of our services can only be prevented in this manner and that this data may enable committed criminal offences to be investigated. In this respect, the storage of this data is necessary for Expert Systems AG security reasons. This data will not be passed on to third parties unless required to do so by law or for the purpose of criminal prosecution.

Registration by voluntarily submitting data also enables us to offer you content or services that may only be offered to registered users due to to the nature of the offer. Registered users are free to modify personal data submitted during registration or have them deleted in entirety from our database at any time, provided that it is no longer needed to fulfil the contract (e.g. if the contract term has not yet expired) or is subject to legal retention periods.

Upon request, we will provide you at any time with information about which personal data we have stored about you.  
Our data protection officer is available as a contact person in this regard.

**3\. Subscription to our newsletter**

Users have the option of subscribing to our newsletter via our websites. The specific personal data you submit to us when signing up to the newsletter is dependent on the type of input mask used.

You can only receive our newsletter if you (1) have a valid email address and (2) have registered for newsletter distribution.

When registering for the newsletter, the IP address provided by your Internet service provider (ISP), date and time of registration will also be stored. The collection of this data is necessary in order to track (potential) misuse of email addresses at a later point in time and therefore fulfils the purpose of legal protection for Expert Systems AG.

Personal data stored within the scope of registration for newsletters will only be used in order to distribute our newsletter. This data will solely be transmitted to CleverReach GmbH & Co. KG, Mühlenstraße 43, 26180 Rastede, to whom our newsletter distribution is contracted. In addition, no data is disclosed to third parties. You can cancel the use of your email address for advertising purposes at any time by clicking "Unsubscribe" at the bottom of the newsletter. You can at any time revoke the consent you have granted for storing personal data in order to receive our newsletter.

**4\. Newsletter tracking**

The Expert Systems AG newsletters contain what are known as tracking pixels. A tracking pixel is a miniature graphic embedded in emails in HTML format for the purposes of recording and analyzing log files. This enables us to conduct a statistic evaluation of the success or failure of our online marketing campaigns. On the basis of the technology used, we can recognize whether and when an email was opened by you and whether you clicked on the links within the email.

Data collected in this manner is stored and evaluated on our account by CleverReach GmbH & Co. KG, Mühlenstraße 43, 26180 Rastede, in order to optimize newsletter distribution and modify the content of future newsletters further so that they match the interests of the person receiving the newsletter. Your data will not be disclosed to any third parties. You can revoke your declaration of consent for this, which you have granted separately, in this regard at any time. To do so, please contact our data protection officer.

**5\. Blog comment feature**

For our blog's comment feature, we use the comment system provided by the web service Disqus. All personal and non-personal data generated (comments, links, usernames, passwords) and submitted (email addresses, third-party login credentials) via the Disqus comment system are sent to the Disqus server, where they are processed and stored. The Terms of Use and policies of Disqus apply with regard to this process [and can be found here](https://help.disqus.com/terms-and-policies).

**6\. Contact options via the websites**

Our websites contains legally required information, which enables us to be contacted rapidly in a direct manner, for instance by email. If you contact us by email or via a contact form, the personal data submitted by you will be stored automatically. We store this voluntarily submitted personal data for purposes of handling or to communicate with you; we will not pass it on to third parties.

**7\. Use and application of third party tools and services on our websites**

We have integrated various third-party components on our websites. primarily for the purpose of optimizing your surfing experience and analyze user behavior on our websites. The following provides you with more information about this:

**a) Google**  
We use various services provided by Google, Inc. on our websites. The operator for the services of Google Remarketing is Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy, Mountain View, CA 94043-1351, USA. The following services are integrated into our websites:

  * **Google Analytics (with anonymization function)**  
The Expert Systems AG has integrated Google Analytics components into its websites.  
The operator for Google Analytics components is Google Inc., 1600 Amphitheatre Pkwy, Mountain View, CA 94043-1351, USA.  
Google complies with the data protection provisions of the Privacy Shield agreement and is registered with the U.S. Department of Commerce's "Privacy Shield" program.  
https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt000000001L5AAI  
Expert Systems uses an anonymization function for web analysis via Google Analytics, which Google uses to shorten and anonymize the IP address of the Internet connection of the person concerned. 

Google Analytics is a web analytics service. Web analytics is the collection, organization and analysis of data on the behavior of visitors to websites. A web analytics service collects, among other things, data on which websites a person concerned came to a website from ("referrer" URLs), which subpages of the websites were accessed or how often and for how long a website was viewed. These web analysis metrics are mainly used as a data basis for optimizing the functions and contents of a website.  
Google Analytics sets a cookie on the computer of the person concerned. The definition of cookies has been provided above. Using cookies enables Google to analyze the use of our websites. Each time a user visits one of the pages of the websites that are operated by Expert Systems AG and upon which Google Analytics components are embedded, the Internet browser on the computer of the person concerned is automatically prompted by the Google Analytics components to transmit data to Google for the purpose of online analysis. As part of this technical procedure, Google obtains knowledge of personal data, such as the IP address of the person concerned, which enables Google to trace the origin of the visitors and their behavior on the site, among other things.  
Cookies are used to store personal information, such as access time, the location from which access came and the frequency of visits to our websites by the person concerned. For every visit to our websites, this personal data, including the IP address of the Internet connection used by the person concerned, will be transferred to Google in the United States of America. This personal data will be stored by Google in the United States of America. Google may disclose the personal data collected through this technical process to third parties.  
You can prevent the setting of cookies by our websites, as described above, at any time via the settings for your Internet browser and thus permanently object to the setting of cookies. This Internet browser setting will also prevent Google from setting a cookie on the computer of the person concerned. In addition, cookies that have already been set by Google Analytics can be deleted via your Internet browser or another software program.  
Furthermore, the person concerned has the option to object to and prevent the recording of data on the use of these websites by Google Analytics and the processing of this data by Google. To do so, the person concerned must download and install a browser add-on under the linkhttps://tools.google.com/dlpage/gaoptout. This browser add-on communicates to Google Analytics via JavaScript that data and information regarding visitors to websites may not be transferred to Google Analytics. The installation of the browser add-on will be considered as an objection by Google. If the information technology system of the person concerned is at a later point in time deleted, formatted or reinstalled, the person concerned must reinstall the browser add-on in order to deactivate Google Analytics. If the browser add-on is uninstalled or deactivated by the person concerned or another person under their authority, it is possible to reinstall or reactivate the browser add-on.

Further information and the Google Analytics Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/ and at http://www.google.com/intl/de/analytics/privacyoverview.html.

  * **Google AdWords**  
Google AdWords is an Internet advertising service that permits advertisers to place ads in Google search engine results and in the Google advertising network. Google AdWords enables advertisers to set predefined keywords: an advertisement will be displayed in Google search results only if the user's search engine results are relevant to the keywords. Within the Google advertising network, advertisements are distributed to thematically relevant websites by means of an automatic algorithm and predefined keywords.

Google AdWords are used for the advertisement of our websites through the placement of interest-based advertisements on websites of other companies and in the search engines results for search engine Google, as well as the placement of third party advertisements on our website.

Should a person arrive at our website via a Google advertisement, a "conversion cookie" will be placed on the computer of that user by Google. The definition of cookies has been provided above. A conversion cookie loses its validity after a limited period of time and is not used to identify the person concerned. If the cookie has not yet expired, the conversion cookie is used to determine whether certain subpages, such as the shopping basket of an online shop system, have been accessed on our website. The conversion cookie enables both us and Google to track whether a person who has placed an ad on our website has generated revenue, that is, whether they have completed or canceled a purchase of goods.

The data and information obtained through the use of conversion cookies are used by Google to create statistics about visits to our website. These visitor statistics are in turn used by us to determine the total number of users who arrived at our website via AdWords advertisements, as well as the success rate of the corresponding AdWord advertisement, and to optimize our AdWords advertisements in the future. Neither our company nor the other clients of Google AdWords receive information from Google which could identify the person concerned.

By means of conversion cookies, personal data is saved, for example the websites that have been visited by the person concerned. For every visit to our websites, therefore, personal data including the IP address of the Internet connection of the person concerned will be transmitted to Google in the United States of America. This personal data will be stored by Google in the United States of America. Google may disclose the personal data collected through this technical process to third parties.

You can prevent the setting of cookies by our websites, as described above, at any time via the settings for your Internet browser and thus permanently object to the setting of cookies. This Internet browser setting will also prevent Google from setting a conversion cookie on the computer of the person concerned. In addition, cookies that have already been set by Google AdWords can be deleted via your Internet browser or another software program.

In addition, the person concerned can choose not to receive interest-based advertising from Google. To do this you need to go to www.google.de/settings/ads on each of the Internet browsers you use and modify the settings there.

Further information and the Google Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/.

  * **Google Optimize**  
Google Optimize is a service to carry out so-called A/B tests - primarily in the field of marketing.  
A, for example, is the original of a subpage of our website, B is a variant of this subpage in which a certain detail has usually been changed, e.g. the color of a button. In the comparison it is then analyzed with which color the button was clicked on more often.  
Further information and the Google Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://www.google.de/intl/de/policies/privacy/.

**b) Microsoft Ads**  
The Expert Systems AG has integrated Microsoft Ads into this website. Microsoft Ads is an Internet advertising service that allows advertisers to place ads both in Microsoft's search engine results and in the Microsoft advertising network. Microsoft Ads allows an advertiser to specify certain keywords in advance, which are used to display an ad in Microsoft's search engine results only when the user uses the search engine to retrieve a keyword-relevant search result. Within the Microsoft advertising network, advertisements are distributed to thematically relevant websites by means of an automatic algorithm and predefined keywords.

The operating company for Microsoft Ads' services is Microsoft Corporation, One Microsoft Way, Redmond, WA 98052-6399, USA.

The purpose of Microsoft Ads is to promote our website by displaying interest-relative advertising on Microsoft.com (and websites operated by Microsoft such as MSN.com, Bing.de and Bing.co.uk), AOL and Yahoo.com (including websites operated by Yahoo). The search network also includes third-party websites operated by Microsoft and Yahoo consortium search partners.

If you access our website via such an advertisement, a cookie is placed on your computer. A conversion cookie loses its validity after thirty days and is not used to identify the person concerned. If the cookie has not yet expired, the conversion cookie is used to determine whether certain subpages, such as the shopping basket of an online shop system, have been accessed on our website. The conversion cookie enables both Microsoft and us to track whether a person affected who came to our website via a Microsoft-Ads advertisement generated revenue, i.e., whether they completed or cancelled a purchase of goods.

A Microsoft UET tag is integrated into our website. This is a code used in connection with the cookie to store personal information, such as the web pages visited by the person concerned. Personal data, including the IP address of the Internet connection used by the person concerned, is therefore transferred to Microsoft in Australia, Austria, Brazil, Canada, Finland, France, Germany, Hong Kong, India, Ireland, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, the Netherlands, Singapore, the United Kingdom and the United States of America each time he or she visits our website. This personal data is stored by Microsoft in Australia, Austria, Brazil, Canada, Finland, France, Germany, Hong Kong, India, Ireland, Japan, Korea, Malaysia, the Netherlands, Singapore, the United Kingdom, and the United States of America.

In addition, Microsoft may be able to track your usage across multiple electronic devices through cross-device tracking, enabling you to display personalized advertising on or in Microsoft webpages and apps.

You can disable this behavior at https://account.microsoft.com/privacy/ad-settings/ (Opt Out).

The person concerned can prevent the saving of cookies through our website at any time, as already described above, by means of an appropriate setting of the Internet browser used and thus permanently object to the setting of cookies. This Internet browser setting will also prevent Microsoft from setting a Microsoft Ads cookie on the information technology system of the person concerned. In addition, a cookie already stored by Microsoft Ads can be deleted at any time via the Internet browser or other software programs.

Furthermore, the person concerned has the possibility to withdraw from interest-related advertising by Microsoft Ads. To do this, the person concerned must select the link https://account.microsoft.com/privacy/ad-settings/ from each of the Internet browsers they use and select the desired settings there.

For more information on Microsoft Ads' analytics services, please visit the Microsoft Ads website (https://help.ads.microsoft.com/#apex/3/de/53056/2). For more information about Microsoft and Microsoft's privacy policy, please see the Microsoft Privacy Policy (https://privacy.microsoft.com/de-de/privacystatement).

**c) LinkedIn**  
LinkedIn is a social network for building and maintaining professional business contacts and offers tailored search functions and tools as part of its talent, marketing and sales offering. Users create a career profile that can be viewed privately and publicly according to their own wishes and settings (see profile settings for data protection and opt out).

LinkedIn is operated by LinkedIn Ireland Unlimited Company, Wilton Place, Dublin 2, Ireland. 

As part of its service offering, LinkedIn collects public information (such as career-related news and achievements) and other content that may include information about the specific LinkedIn user (such as mentions in articles, posts, comments). You can choose to opt out of this. As a targeted social media network with millions of global users, LinkedIn is also a B2B advertising medium for companies through which different ad formats can be targeted to different users. LinkedIn does not share personal data with third parties for their direct marketing purposes without the user's consent; see profile settings for advertisements and opt-out and opt-out for surveys and services).LinkedIn stores cookies and similar technologies (e.g. web beacons, pixels, ad tags, device identifiers) to recognize the user and his or her platform both off- and on the platform. Users can restrict this tracking within the display preferences under the Guest Controls.

Expert Systems AG operates its own LinkedIn profile to advertise career opportunities on the one hand, and to advertise specific Expert Systems products on the other. Every Expert Systems AG post on the company profile shows how many users have carried out a specific action organically or through paid advertising. Expert Systems AG also sponsors content via LinkedIn in the form of sponsored posts, text ads, and videos. In addition to the organic reach of the followers, these advertisements are aimed at specific target groups. Target groups can be created based on various targeting options, e.g. by location, professional title, skills, and interests. LinkedIn uses the user's own profile information and targets the individual user approvals that the user has configured in his profile. Expert Systems AG receives information on the effectiveness of advertisements by tracking user behavior via cookies and similar technologies. Depending on the advertising campaign, the LinkedIn Insight Tag and specific LinkedIn scripts installed on our homepage measure whether a specific product has been added to the shopping cart or purchased. If preferred, the user can limit this in the LinkedIn display settings.

Further information on data protection LinkedIn can be found in the data protection regulation  
s (https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy?_l=en_EN)

**d) Messagebird**  
Messagebird is an SMS service provider through which our customers can invite end users to their surveys via SMS.  
Further information and Messagebird's current privacy policy can be found at https://www.messagebird.com/de-de/legal/privacy

**e) Userlike**  
Userlike provides us with a live chat with which we can clarify service requests and orders with our customers in real time.  
Further information and Userlike's applicable privacy policy can be found at https://www.userlike.com/de/terms

**f) Fastbill Monsum**  
FastBill Monsum provides us with an accounting system through which, for example, invoices are managed and created and in which the technical and personal master data for the user account is stored.  
Further information and FastBill Monsum's current privacy policy can be found at https://www.fastbill.com/datenschutz

**g) Wirecard AG**  
Wirecard AG is our banking service provider, which guarantees all payment modalities for contractual fulfilment, e.g. the collection of the invoice amount by SEPA direct debit mandate or by credit card.  
Further information and the Wirecard AG Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://www.wirecard.com/privacy-protection/.

**h) PayPal S.à.r.l.**  
PayPal S.à.r.l. is another banking service provider that processes the payment of invoices via PayPal.  
Further information and PayPal's current privacy policy can be found at https://www.paypal.com/de/webapps/mpp/ua/privacy-full?locale.x=en_DE can be retrieved.

**i) CentralStation**  
CentralStation is a software for customer data management. Personal data such as communication data are stored here in order to be able to contact customers quickly and easily and to have an insight into the contact history to date.  
Further information and CentralStation's current privacy policy can be found at https://centralstationcrm.de/datenschutz

**j) SalesForce**  
SalesForce is a software for customer data management. Personal data such as communication data are stored here in order to be able to contact customers quickly and easily and to have an insight into the contact history to date.  
Further information and the SalesForce Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://www.salesforce.com/de/company/privacy/

**k) Telekom**  
Deutsche Telekom is our hosting service provider and provides us with the servers we need to provide you with our services.  
Further information and the applicable data protection regulations of Deutsche Telekom can be found at https://www.t-systems.com/de/en/data-protection

**l) CleverReach**  
We make use of the services of CleverReach in order to send our users and customers mailings and newsletters with interesting information and offers.  
Further information and the applicable CleverReach privacy policy can be found at https://www.cleverreach.com/en/privacy-policy/

**m) Join.me**  
Join.me is used to enable interested parties and customers to participate in screen presentations (such as product training) and online meetings.  
Further information and Join.me's current privacy policy can be found at https://www.logmeininc.com/de/legal/privacy

**n) Microsoft**  
We use the e-mail and office software cloud for internal work, but also to process service requests - and orders.  
Further information and the Microsoft Privacy Policy can be viewed at https://privacy.microsoft.com/de-de/privacystatement.

**Tracking and advertising service providers**

**a) Criteo**  
This website uses Criteo, a service of Criteo SA, 32 Rue Blanche, 75009 Paris, France. Criteo is a web analysis service. Criteo collects and uses technical data about your surfing behavior to show you personalized advertising. Criteo collects, for example, events related to your activities on our website (e.g. the number of pages viewed, the products viewed on the site, your search queries on the website), information related to your device (device type, operating system, version) and events related to the Criteo ad serving activities such as the number of ads displayed to you. Criteo uses cookies for this purpose. Criteo does not collect any personal data. More information about this can be found at http://www.criteo.com/de/datenschutzrichtlinie. Under the following link you can deactivate the display of Criteo advertising material: http://www.criteo.com/de/datenschutzrichtlinie

**b) Facebook plugins (Like & Share Button)**  
Our pages include plugins from the social network Facebook provided by Facebook Inc, 1 Hacker Way, Menlo Park, California 94025, USA. You can recognize the Facebook plugins by the Facebook logo or the "Like" button on our page. An overview of the Facebook plugins can be found here: https://developers.facebook.com/docs/plugins/.

When you visit our pages, the plugin establishes a direct connection between your browser and the Facebook server. Facebook receives the information that you have visited our site with your IP address. If you click the Facebook "Like" button while logged into your Facebook account, you can link the contents of our pages on your Facebook profile. This allows Facebook to associate the visit to our pages with your user account. We would like to point out that, as the provider of the pages, we have no knowledge of the content of the data transmitted or of their use by Facebook. For more information, please see Facebook's Privacy Policy at: https://de-de.facebook.com/policy.php.

If you do not want Facebook to associate your visit to our pages with your Facebook account, please log out of your Facebook account.

**c) Facebook Pixel / Remarketing / Custom Audiences**  
Our online offer uses so-called "Facebook pixels" of the social network Facebook, which is operated by Facebook Inc, 1 Hacker Way, Menlo Park, CA 94025, USA, or, if you are based in the EU, Facebook Ireland Ltd, 4 Grand Canal Square, Grand Canal Harbour, Dublin 2, Ireland ("Facebook"). With the help of the Facebook pixel, Facebook is able to determine the visitors of our offer as a target group for the presentation of advertisements, so-called "Facebook ads". Accordingly, we use the Facebook pixel to display the Facebook ads we post only to Facebook users who have shown an interest in our website. This means that with the help of the Facebook pixel we want to make sure that our Facebook ads correspond to the potential interest of the users and are not a nuisance. The Facebook pixel also helps us track the effectiveness of Facebook ads for statistical and market research purposes by showing whether users have been redirected to our site after clicking on a Facebook ad.

The Facebook pixel is integrated directly by Facebook when you visit our websites and can store a so-called cookie, i.e. a small file, on your device. If you then log in to Facebook or visit Facebook when logged in, the visit to our site will be recorded in your profile. The data collected about you is anonymous to us, so it does not provide us with any information about the identity of the user. However, Facebook stores and processes the data so that a connection to the respective user profile is possible. Facebook processes the data in accordance with Facebook's Data Usage Policy. Accordingly, you can find more information about how the remarketing pixel works and how Facebook ads are displayed in general in the Facebook Data Usage Policy: https://www.facebook.com/policy.php.  
You can object to the collection by the Facebook pixel and use of your data to display Facebook ads. To do this, you can visit the page set up by Facebook and follow the instructions on the settings for usage-based advertising: https://www.facebook.com/settings?tab=ads or declare the objection via the US page http://www.aboutads.info/choices/ or the EU page http://www.youronlinechoices.com/. The settings are platform-independent, i.e. they are applied to all devices, such as desktop computers or mobile devices.

Moreover, we are using Facebook's advertising feature "Custom Audiences from File" based on our legitimate interests. In this case, some of the data provided by customers in their ProvenExpert account, if available (email address, phone number, city, zip code, first name, last name), are uploaded by us to the Facebook Ads Manager. The data are uploaded to Facebook servers in hashed format. The upload of this data has the sole purpose of matching users from our customer database against Facebook's user database in order to make sure that our Facebook ads can be delivered to the people that have a particular interest in our information and offers based on their use of our products and services. You may opt out of our use of your data for this purpose at any time by visiting https://www.facebook.com/ads/preferences/ and removing Facebook pages by ProvenExpert under "Advertisers and Businesses".

**d) Twitter**  
This website uses Twitter Universal Tag from Twitter Inc. to track events and page views. This allows us granular Twitter advertising. For details on how Twitter handles your personal data and your rights in this regard, please refer to the Twitter data protection information.

https://ads.twitter.com/terms/us

An opt-out is also possible via the http://optout.aboutads.info page.

**e) LinkedIn Insight Tag and Matched Audiences**  
This website uses LinkedIn Insight Tag from LinkedIn Ireland, Wilton Plaza, Wilton Place, Dublin 2, Ireland ("LinkedIn"). LinkedIn Insight Tag is a re-targeting and analysis tool which creates a cookie, a tiny text file, to be placed in your web browser when you visit the ProvenExpert website. The Insight tag is integrated into this website and enables the collection of data such as your IP address or the time of accessing this website or the collection of defined events (such as downloads or page views). In addition, relevant offers and recommendations specific to your interests can be displayed, depending on which services, information and offers you have informed yourself about on our website. Furthermore, LinkedIn can compile statistics with aggregated data about the use and visit of our website. If you are a LinkedIn member, demographic information, such as your approximate location, may also be collected. The cookie stored by the Insight Tag in your browser remains there until it is manually deleted by you or is automatically deleted 6 months after the last loading of the Insight Tag.

You can prevent the storage of cookies via your browser settings. Alternatively, you may opt out of the use of LinkedIn Insight Tag by setting an opt-out cookie which remains on your device until you delete all cookies on that device. You can activate the opt-out cookie here: https://www.linkedin.com/psettings/guest-controls/retargeting-opt-out. If you are a LinkedIn member, click on "Opt-out on LinkedIn". Non-members shoudl click on "Opt-out".

Moreover, we are using LinkedIn's advertising feature "Matched Audiences" based on our legitimate interests. In this case, the email address provided by our customers in their ProvenExpert account is uploaded by us to the LinkedIn Campaign Manager tool. The data are uploaded to LinkedIn servers in hashed format. The upload of this data has the sole purpose of matching users from our customer database against LinkedIn's user database in order to make sure that our Facebook ads can be delivered to the people that we consider to have a particular interest in our information and offers based on their use of our products and services. You may opt out of our use of your data for this purpose at any time by visiting https://www.linkedin.com/psettings/advertising/actions-that-showed-interest and setting the selection switch to "No" under "Interactions with Businesses".

LinkedIn is certified under the EU-U.S. Privacy Shield, which is a data protection agreement intended to assure responsible data transfers and data protection standards to certified US-based businesses. This certification has been approved by the EU commission within the decision of 12 July 2016 (file no. C(2016) 4176).

You can find LinkedIn's current certification status according to EU-US Privacy Shield here: https://www.privacyshield.gov/participant?id=a2zt0000000L0UZAA0.

The processing of your data is based on Art. 6 Par. 1 f) GDPR (Balancing of Interest) and on our legitimate interest to serve interest-based information, offers and advertisement to our customers and website visitors.

Further information about data protection at LinkedIn can be obtained here: https://www.linkedin.com/legal/privacy-policy#choices-oblig

**f) The Reach Group**  
Expert Systems AG uses the services of The Reach Group GmbH (Am Karlsbad 16, 10785 Berlin), an agency for digital advertising formats. The Reach Group GmbH uses the following services/providers:  
NEORY: NEORY GmbH, based in Brandschachtstraße 2, 44149 Dortmund, Germany, is a technology provider for the provision and optimized delivery of advertising materials.  
Further information on data protection at NEORY can be found here: https://www.neory.com/privacy.html

EASY Marketing: EASY Marketing GmbH based in Asselner Hellweg 124,  
44319 Dortmund is a technology provider for the provision and optimized delivery of advertising materials.  
Further information on data protection at EASY Marketing can be found here: https://www.easy-m.de/privacy.html

**g) Quantcast**  
This website uses the Quantcast services for user measurement and advertising purposes. As part of these services, the Quantcast site allows anonymous browser data to be collected and analyzed using standard Internet cookies. These anonymous data are in no case used to personally identify the visitors of the website. Learn more about Quantcast's commitment to confidentiality and privacy in the Quantcast Privacy Policy. You can opt-out of advertising and data collection through Quantcast on the Quantcast opt out page or through the more advanced opt out service provided by the European Digital Advertising Alliance.  
For more information about Quantcast's privacy policy, please visit: https://www.quantcast.com/de/datenschutz/

**h) ADITION conversion pixel & Adition Retargeting Pixels**  
ADITION technologies AG, headquartered at Oststraße 55, 40211 Düsseldorf, Germany, is a technology provider for the provision and optimized delivery of advertising materials.  
Further information on data protection at ADITION can be found here: https://www.adition.com/datenschutz/

**i) Plista**  
Plista presents the visitors of websites in the plista network, i.e. websites on which plista services are used, individual recommendations regarding content and advertisements.

This is done by either (i) recommending content to visitors based on their interests, (ii) recommending content based on the interests of similar users, or (iii) recommending content that they have previously viewed on websites outside the plista network.

For this it is necessary that plista analyses the interests of the visitors and can distinguish the visitors individually from each other. This is done through the use of cookies.

Further information on data protection at plista can be found here: https://www.plista.com/about/privacy/

**k) Taboola**  
We use Taboola (One Euston Square, 40 Melton Street, 13th Floor, London, NW1 2FD) on our website. This makes it possible to recommend content that fits your personal interests and thus to design our offer individually for you. Taboola uses cookies to determine which websites you visit frequently and how you navigate our website. For this purpose, device-related data and protocol data are collected and user profiles are generated through the use of pseudonyms. These usage profiles are not combined with data about the bearer of the pseudonym and do not allow any conclusions to be drawn about your personal data. Your IP address, for example, will be transmitted to Taboola in abbreviated form. More information about Taboola can be found at www.taboola.com/privacy-policy. You can find a way to deactivate the service on the Digital Advertising Alliance website at http://www.aboutads.info/choices/. You can also prevent the storage of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings in your browser software.

**l) AppNexus**  
AppNexus Inc. is a New York (US)-headquartered advertising technology company.

AppNexus offers online auction infrastructure and technology for data management, optimization, financial clearing and support for directly negotiated advertising campaigns. It has both demand-side platform (DSP) and supply-side platform (SSP) functionalities. It integrates with advertising sources including Google's DoubleClick, Microsoft's AdECN, engage:BDR and other aggregators. It operates out of multiple data centers, including one in Amsterdam serving Europe and the Middle East, in a facility shared with Equinix.

Further information on data protection at AppNexus can be found here:  
https://www.appnexus.com/platform-privacy-policy 

**Further suppliers**

**a) Cisionpoint**  
We use the online tool Cisionpoint from CISION Germany GmbH as a fully integrated PR management solution to manage our press distribution lists and send press releases to media representatives.

Further information and the applicable CISION data protection regulations can be found at http://www.cision.de/datenschutzerklaerung/

**b) Trello**  
Trello is a web-based project management software operated by Atlassian. We use this to plan projects (including customer-oriented projects) and create editorial plans. In the web-optimized application it is possible to create lists together with other members on so-called boards. They can be edited as required and provided with checklists, attachments and a fixed date.  
Further information and the applicable privacy policies of Trello, Inc. can be found at https://trello.com/privacy

**c) Slack**  
Slack is a web-based instant messaging service from Slack Technologies, which we use for direct, fast communication within the team.

Further information and the applicable privacy policy of Trello, Inc. can be found at https://slack.com/intl/de-de/privacy-policy and in the updated version valid from 25.5.2018 at https://trello.com/privacy-updated

**d) Social Hub**  
The SocialHub online platform of maloon GmbH offers us the opportunity to respond faster and more efficiently to social media conversations. In addition, we plan and post contributions on our social media channels via SocialHub.

Further information and the applicable privacy policy of Trello, Inc. can be found at https://socialhub.io/de/recht/datenschutz/

**8\. Privacy policy for the payment methods offered**

**a) PayPal**  
Expert Systems AG has integrated PayPal components on its website. PayPal is an online payment service provider. PayPal makes it possible to initiate online payments to or to receive payments from third parties. PayPal also acts as a trustee and provides buyer protection services.

The European operating company of PayPal is PayPal (Europe) S.à.r.l. & Cie. S.C.A., 22-24 Boulevard Royal, 2449 Luxembourg, Luxemburg.

If you select "PayPal" as a payment option in our online shop during the order process, your data will be automatically transmitted to PayPal. By selecting this payment option, you consent to the transfer of personal data required for payment processing.

The personal data transmitted to PayPal is usually first name, last name, address, email address, IP address, telephone number, mobile phone number or other data required for payment processing. Personal data in connection with the respective order are also necessary for the processing of the purchase contract.

The purpose of data transmission is to process payments and prevent fraud. Expert Systems AG will provide PayPal with personal data in particular if there is a legitimate interest in the transfer. Personal data exchanged between PayPal and Expert Systems AG may be transferred by PayPal to credit agencies. The purpose of this transfer is to verify identity and creditworthiness.

PayPal may pass on personal data to affiliated companies and service providers or subcontractors if this is necessary to fulfil contractual obligations or if the data is to be processed on behalf of PayPal.

The person concerned has the option to revoke his or her consent to the handling of personal data by PayPal at any time. A revocation does not affect personal data which must be processed, used or transmitted for (contractual) payment processing.

PayPal's current privacy policy can be found at https://www.paypal.com/de/webapps/mpp/ua/privacy-full.

**b) Other payment options**  
You enter your payment data (e.g. if you opt for a SEPA direct debit mandate or credit card payment) on a separate website in your user account.  
The payment data are then collected by the providers, without us being able to view or access them.

C. Your rights regarding the processing of personal data in detail

Insofar as we store your personal data or process this in additional ways, special legal rights apply (the "rights of the person affected"), which we will briefly outline here.

**1\. Right to access information**

In addition to your right to information, you have the right to request confirmation from us at any time and free of charge as to what personal data is stored about you. In addition you have the right to receive a copy of this information. The right to access information additionally covers:

  * the purpose for which the data is processed;
  * the categories of personal data that are processed;
  * the recipient or categories of recipients to whom the personal data has been or will be made available, in particular recipients in third countries or international organizations;
  * where possible, the planned duration for which the personal data will be saved or, where this is not possible to establish, the criteria for determining this duration;
  * the existence of a right to rectification or deletion of the personal data or to limit processing of this data by the party responsible or right to object to the processing of same;
  * the existence of a right to appeal through a supervisory authority;
  * the existence of an automated decision including profiling in accordance with Article 22 Para. 1 and 4 of the Data Protection Regulation and, at least in these cases, the existence of meaningful information regarding the logic involved, as well as the scope and the desired effects of such processing on you.

You also have a right of access to information on whether personal data has been transferred to a non-EU country or to an international organization. If this is the case, you also have the right to obtain information about the appropriate guarantees in connection with the transmission.

You can contact our data protection officer at any time if you want to exercise this right to information.

**2\. Right to correction**

You have the right to request that incorrect personal data concerning you be promptly corrected. You also have the right, taking into account the purposes of the processing, to request the completion of incomplete personal data, also by means of a supplementary declaration.

You can contact our data protection officer at any time if you want to exercise this right to correction.

**3\. Right to deletion (Right to be forgotten)**

You have the right to request us to promptly delete the personal data concerning you, providing that one of the following reasons applies and as long as the processing is not necessary:

  * The personal data has been collected or processed for reasons that are no longer necessary.
  * You revoke your consent on which the processing was based pursuant to Art. 6 Para. 1 Letter a of the GDPR and there is no other legal basis for processing.
  * You object to the processing pursuant to Art. 21 Para. 1 GDPR and there are no overriding legitimate and justified reasons for the processing on our part, or you object to the processing pursuant to Art. 21 Para. 2 of the GDPR in the case of data processing for advertising purposes.
  * The personal data has been unlawfully processed by us.
  * Deletion of personal data is necessary for complying with a legal obligation under Union law or the law of the Member States to which we are subject.
  * The personal data was collected in relation to information society services according to Art. 8 Para. 1 of the GDPR.

Provided that one of the aforementioned reasons applies and you wish to have the personal data stored by us deleted, you can contact our data protection officer with your request at any time. They will then ensure that the request for the deletion is promptly complied with.

In general, we do not release any personal data publicly. However, should we release personal data publicly and as the responsible party be obliged to delete personal data pursuant to Art. 17 Para. 1 GDPR, we will take appropriate measures (also of a technical nature), under consideration of the technology available and the cost of implementation, in order to inform other persons responsible for data processing and who process the published personal data that you have requested that these other persons responsible for data processing delete all links to this personal data as well as its copies and replications, insofar the processing is not necessary. Our data protection officer will take the necessary steps in individual cases.

**4\. Right to restrict processing**

  * You dispute the accuracy of the personal data for a period of time that allows us to verify the accuracy of this data.
  * The processing is unlawful, you reject the deletion of personal data and instead request a restriction of the use of the personal data.
  * We no longer need the personal data for processing reasons, however, you yourself require the data in order to assert, exercise or defend legal claims.
  * You object to the processing pursuant to Art. 21 Para. 1 of the GDPR at it is not yet clear whether the legitimate reasons on our part outweigh your legitimate interests.

Provided that one of the aforementioned conditions is met and you wish to restrict the personal data stored by us, you can contact our data protection officer at any time. They will then ensure that the data processing is restricted.

**5\. Right to data portability**

You have the right to receive the personal data concerning you that you have provided us with in a structured, standard machine-readable format. You also have the right to request us to transmit this information to another person responsible, provided that the processing is based on consent pursuant to Art. 6 Para. 1 Letter a of the GDPR or a contract pursuant to Art. 6 Para. 1 Letter b of the GDPR and providing that the processing is carried out using automated methods.

When exercising your right to data portability pursuant to Art. 20 Para. 1 of the GDPR, you also have the right to have us transfer the personal data directly to another person responsible, as long as this is technically feasible and provided that the rights and freedoms of other persons are not affected by this.

You can contact our data protection officer directly and at any time to assert the right to data portability.

**6\. Right to objection**

At any time, for reasons specific to you, you have the right to object to the processing of personal data concerning yourself that has been carried out on the basis of Art. 6 Para. 1 Letter f of the GDPR in order to protect our legitimate interests. This also applies to profiling based on this regulation.

In the case of of an objection, we will no longer process the personal data, unless we can prove compelling grounds for processing that outweigh your interests, rights and freedoms as the person concerned or unless the processing is intended to assert, exercise or defend legal claims.

Should we process personal data for direct marketing purposes, you have the right to object at any time to the personal data being processed for this purpose. This also applies to profiling, should this be directly related to this direct marketing. If you object to data processing for direct advertising purposes, we will no longer process your personal data for this reason.

You can contact our data protection officer at any time to assert the right to objection.

**7\. Right to revoke data protection consent**

You have the right to revoke your consent to the processing of personal data at any time.

If you want to exercise your right to revoke the consent, you can contact our data protection officer at any time.

**8\. Right of appeal to a regulatory body**

You have the right to lodge a complaint with a local regulatory body.

Contact details of the responsible local supervisory authority:

**Berlin Officer for Data Protection and Freedom of Information**  
Friedrichstr. 219  
10969 Berlin

Telephone: +49 (0)30 13889-0  
Fax: +49 (0)30 2155050

E-Mail: [mailbox@datenschutz-berlin.de](mailto:mailbox@datenschutz-berlin.de)

D. Our legal basis for the processing of your data

**1\. Legitimate interest**

According to Article 6 (1) f) of the GDPR, we are permitted to process your data even without express consent, provided that if this is necessary to safeguard our legitimate interests or those of a third party, as long as your interests or your fundamental rights and freedoms requiring the protection of personal data, do not outweigh this.

We do not believe that the following activities adversely affect persons in any way. On the contrary, they help us provide more tailored and efficient services to you and are therefore beneficial to all parties. However, you still have the right to object to our processing of your personal data on this basis, as mentioned above.

**User and customer data:**  
We must ensure that our business activities run smoothly, so that we can continue to provide you with our products and services of the usual quality and at a reasonable price. For this reason, we require your data in order to fulfill our contracts with you, to bill you for our services and supply you with our products, to answer your support queries and so that we can provide you with updates and patches for your software. Lastly, we also require your data in order to protect our intellectual property in the form of our software and content from misuse and piracy by using the data stored in your user account. It is therefore in our legitimate interests to use your data.

We have our own legal obligations and it is in our legitimate interest to insist on their fulfillment. If we believe in good faith that this is necessary, we may therefore disclose your information for the purposes of law enforcement or tax collection or actual or threatened disputes.

**Evaluator data:**  
When you submit a review, we collect your personal data to prevent misuse (e.g. through multiple reviews).

**Website visitors:**  
We collect a limited amount of information from visitors to our websites and use it to help you navigate our websites and better manage the services we offer. The data we collect in this way comprises information about how you use our website and how often you access it.

**2\. Agreement**

Under certain circumstances, we may need your consent to process your personal data in connection with certain activities. Depending on what exactly your data is needed for, we will either ask for your explicit consent via "opt-in" or silent consent via soft opt-in .

According to Article 4(11) of the GDPR, consent (via opt-in) is classed as "any voluntary declaration of intent, in an informed and unequivocal manner, in the form of a declaration or other clear affirmative act, with which the person concerned indicates their consent to the processing of personal data concerning themselves". Put simply, this means that:

  * you must voluntarily give us your consent without us putting any kind of pressure on you;
  * you must know what you are granting consent for - we will therefore ensure that we have provided you with sufficient information; and
  * you must give us your consent in the form of a positive, affirmative act. In most cases, we will provide you with a field that you must mark so that this requirement is clearly and unambiguously fulfilled.

We keep a record of the consent that you have given in this way.

As previously mentioned, in some cases consent by soft opt-in is sufficient. We may advertise products and services that are related to the products we offer (especially our software and the content we offer) and services (for example in the hosting area), provided that you have not actively unsubscribed from these communications.

As previously mentioned, you have the right to revoke your consent to these activities. by contacting our data security officer 

**3\. Assertion, exercise or defence of legal rights**

Sometimes it may be necessary for us to process personal data in connection to the pursuit or defence of legal claims. This may occur, for example, if we require legal advice in relation to legal proceedings or are legally obliged to retain or disclose certain information in the course of legal proceedings.

Part 4 - Definitions

The Expert Systems AG Privacy Policy is based on terms used by the European directive and regulation provider at the point when the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) was issued. Our Privacy Policy is intended to be easy to read and understandable for the public as well as for our customers and business partners. Therefore, we would like to explain in advance the terms used.

In this privacy statement, we use the following terms amongst others:

  * **"personal data"** : Personal data is all the information which refers to an identified or identifiable natural person. A natural person is identifiable when they can be identified directly or indirectly, in particular by assignment to an identifier such as a name, an identification number, location data, an online identifier or one or more special characteristics that express the physical, physiological, genetic, psychological, economic, cultural or social identity of this natural person.
  * **"person concerned"** : A person concerned is any identified or identifiable natural person whose personal data is processed by us.
  * **"processing"** : Processing is any operation or series of operations carried out with or without the aid of automated procedures in connection with personal data. These include, but are not limited to, the collection, arrangement, storage, adaptation or alteration, reading, retrieval, use, disclosure by transmission, comparison or linking, restriction, deletion or destruction of personal data.
  * **"profiling"** : Profiling is any kind of automatic processing of personal data that involves using this personal data to assess certain personal aspects that refer to a natural person, especially in order to analyze or predict aspects related to work performance, economic condition, health, personal tastes, interests, reliability, behavior, place of residence or relocation of this natural person. As a responsible company, we refrain from using any sort of profiling.
  * **"Pseudonymization"** : Pseudonymization refers to the processing of personal data in a way in which it can no longer be assigned to the specific person concerned without the use of additional information.
  * **"responsible party"** : The responsible party is a natural or legal person, authority, institution or other body that alone or together with others decides on the purposes and means of personal data processing.
  * **"Auftragsverarbeiter"** : Auftragsverarbeiter ist eine natürliche oder juristische Person, Behörde, Einrichtung oder andere Stelle, die personenbezogene Daten im Auftrag des Verantwortlichen verarbeitet.
  * **"receiver"** : A receiver is a natural or legal person, authority, institution or other body that discloses personal data, regardless of whether this is relating to a third party or not. However, authorities which may receive personal data under Union law or the law of the Member States within the framework of a particular investigation mandate are not considered as recipients.
  * **"third party"** : A third party is a a natural or legal person, authority, institution or other body other than the person concerned, the responsible party, the data processor and persons authorized to process the personal data under the direct responsibility of the person responsible or the data processor.
